<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Bruna Wundervald on Bruna Wundervald</title>
    <link>https://alison.rbind.io/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Bruna Wundervald on Bruna Wundervald</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <copyright>&amp;copy; 2018 Bruna Wundervald</copyright>
    <lastBuildDate>Wed, 20 Apr 2016 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <atom:link href="/" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    <item>
      <title>1st Meetup R-Ladies Curitiba</title>
      <link>https://alison.rbind.io/talk/rladies-dplyr/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 18 Jun 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://alison.rbind.io/talk/rladies-dplyr/</guid>
      <description>
&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;https://alison.rbind.io/img/ohsu-os-panel.png&#34; /&gt;
    
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;The landscape of scientific communication is changing dramatically.  Diverse stakeholders, including major funders and universities are demonstrating a growing interest and investment in open scientific principles and practices.  Researchers, students, and the institutions that support them are needing to navigate new expectations, workflows, and policies against a backdrop of relatively unchanged means and measures of scientific success.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Sound complicated?  Join us on December 8th from 3:00 to 4:00 PM for a panel discussion with OHSU leaders and early career researchers on the evolving landscape of scientific communication.  We’ll explore the drivers behind the calls for “openness”, what this means in practice, and the real world compatibility and tensions between open science and student, researcher, and institutional success.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Confirmed panelists include:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Dr. Gary Westbrook, Vollum Institute Senior Scientist and Director of the Neuroscience Graduate Program&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Dr. Bita Moghaddam, Chair of the Department of Behavioral Neuroscience&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Dr. Abhinav Nellore, Assistant Professor, Biomedical Engineering and the Department of Surgery&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Dr. Alison Hill, Associate Professor, Center for Spoken Language Understanding&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The panel will be followed by food, drinks, and two hands on workshops from 4:00 - 5:30:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;https://alison.rbind.io/img/ohsu-os-labhub-workshop.png&#34; /&gt;
    
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;In this workshop, Dr. Alison Hill and Robin Champieux demonstrated tools and methods for building transparency within a lab, and onboarding new graduate students and postdocs. We provided a &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/apreshill/labhub&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;template GitHub repository&lt;/a&gt; and code of conduct designed to facilitate a healthy and productive learning and research environment. You are encouraged to use these tools to communicate expectations, document protocols, receive feedback, and facilitate the long-term value of students’ and trainees’ contributions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Labhub is a &lt;em&gt;work in progress&lt;/em&gt;. We created &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/apreshill/labhub&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;this repository&lt;/a&gt; as an education and demonstration tool for faculty, postdocs, and students curious about how documentation, open science workflows, and tools like Github can contribute to a healthy and productive research environment. Your ideas and contributions are welcome!&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Music Information Retrieval in R</title>
      <link>https://alison.rbind.io/project/r_music/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 15 Jun 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://alison.rbind.io/project/r_music/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Improving spoken language use (i.e., discourse skills) is a common treatment goal for children with neurodevelopmental disorders, particularly for those with difficulties in conversational reciprocity, perseverative speech, or idiosyncratic/stereotyped word use. These features are clinically meaningful, and in previous projects, we have successfully applied Natural Language Processing (NLP) methods to measure these discourse skills using natural language samples from children with Autism Spectrum Disorder (ASD). However, while NLP methods yield diagnostically relevant measures, it is not known if they can be translated into meaningful outcome measures. To take this next step, important questions must be addressed:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;How stable and responsive are NLP discourse measures over time?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;How consistent are the measures across different measurement contexts and lengths?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;What is their validity?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;To what degree are measures impacted by general language or intellectual abilities?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Lack of knowledge about these psychometric properties of NLP discourse measures is a problem because, without it, the likelihood that children’s use of spoken language can be targeted and impacted in large-scale clinical trials is remote.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The long-term goal of this project is to harness the benefits of NLP to impact functional spoken language outcomes for children with neurodevelopmental disorders. The parent project (R01DC012033: “Computational Characterization of Language Use in Autism Spectrum Disorder”) took the first steps towards this goal by developing NLP algorithms to measure discourse skills based on raw (i.e., not coded or annotated) transcripts. Our strong results indicate difficulties in conversational reciprocity as well as elevated repetitive language behaviors among children with ASD compared to children without ASD, and were not due to differences in age, IQ, or language abilities. Our objective in this project is to take the next step to evaluate the suitability of these NLP automated discourse measures (ADMs) as outcomes for individuals with a range of intellectual abilities and diagnoses. Our approach will focus on optimizing stability of such measures, and assessing responsiveness to change over time, consistency across sampling contexts and sample lengths, and validity.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Shiny Applications for Teaching &amp; Learning</title>
      <link>https://alison.rbind.io/project/shiny_education/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 15 Jun 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://alison.rbind.io/project/shiny_education/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;h1 id=&#34;the-female-clinical-presentation-of-autism-spectrum-disorder-asd-is-not-well-understood-and-is-a-contributing-factor-to-underidentification-and-delays-in-the-diagnosis-of-asds-among-females-particularly-for-those-who-are-verbal-and-without-cognitive-impairments-sex-differences-in-clinical-presentation-may-make-it-more-difficult-to-recognize-asd-symptoms-in-females-yet-evidence-for-differences-between-females-and-males-in-the-two-core-symptom-domains-social-communication-interaction-and-repetitive-behaviors-and-restricted-interests-has-been-inconsistent-although-some-studies-have-found-stronger-social-communication-interaction-skills-in-affected-females-than-in-males-researchers-and-clinicians-have-cautioned-that-these-strengths-may-be-superficial-and-allow-females-to-mask-their-asd-symptoms-further-contributing-to-underidentification-among-females-similarly-restricted-and-repetitive-behaviors-may-be-less-common-among-females-with-asd-or-they-may-simply-look-different-from-clinical-expectations-based-on-male-presentations-again-allowing-females-to-fly-under-the-radar-thus-there-is-a-critical-need-to-further-understanding-of-sex-differences-in-the-fundamental-patterns-of-behavioral-and-social-functioning-relevant-to-the-clinical-presentation-of-asd-in-the-absence-of-such-knowledge-females-with-asd-will-continue-to-be-underidentified-affected-females-will-be-identified-at-older-ages-and-thus-will-fail-to-benefit-from-access-to-early-intervention-services&#34;&gt;The female clinical presentation of Autism Spectrum Disorder (ASD) is not well understood, and is a contributing factor to underidentification and delays in the diagnosis of ASDs among females, particularly for those who are verbal and without cognitive impairments. Sex differences in clinical presentation may make it more difficult to recognize ASD symptoms in females, yet evidence for differences between females and males in the two core symptom domains—social communication/interaction and repetitive behaviors and restricted interests—has been inconsistent. Although some studies have found stronger social communication/interaction skills in affected females than in males, researchers and clinicians have cautioned that these strengths may be superficial and allow females to “mask” their ASD symptoms, further contributing to underidentification among females. Similarly, restricted and repetitive behaviors may be less common among females with ASD, or they may simply look different from clinical expectations based on male presentations, again allowing females to “fly under the radar.” Thus, there is a critical need to further understanding of sex differences in the fundamental patterns of behavioral and social functioning relevant to the clinical presentation of ASD. In the absence of such knowledge, females with ASD will continue to be underidentified; affected females will be identified at older ages and thus will fail to benefit from access to early intervention services.&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&#34;the-long-term-goal-of-this-project-is-to-further-understanding-of-the-female-clinical-presentation-of-asd-so-that-improved-methods-for-identification-assessment-and-treatment-of-females-with-communication-difficulties-such-as-asd-can-be-developed-our-objective-is-to-identify-features-that-characterize-atypical-language-use-a-core-symptom-of-asd-among-females-with-asd-in-the-parent-r01-we-have-developed-and-validated-new-natural-language-processing-based-methods-that-automatically-measure-features-of-atypical-language-use-based-on-raw-i-e-not-coded-transcripts-of-natural-language-samples-our-strong-preliminary-data-indicate-significant-impairments-in-conversational-reciprocity-and-repetitive-speech-behaviors-among-children-with-asd-for-this-administrative-supplement-we-propose-to-increase-sample-size-of-females-with-asd-in-order-to-increase-statistical-power-to-analyze-sex-differences-among-children-with-asd-in-atypical-language-use-our-rationale-for-this-project-is-that-successful-identification-of-observable-and-objective-differences-and-similarities-between-females-and-males-in-atypical-language-use-would-allow-clinicians-to-better-recognize-assess-and-potentially-treat-symptoms-of-asd-in-females&#34;&gt;The long-term goal of this project is to further understanding of the female clinical presentation of ASD, so that improved methods for identification, assessment, and treatment of females with communication difficulties such as ASD can be developed. Our objective is to identify features that characterize atypical language use—a core symptom of ASD—among females with ASD. In the parent R01, we have developed and validated new Natural Language Processing based methods that automatically measure features of atypical language use based on raw (i.e., not coded) transcripts of natural language samples. Our strong preliminary data indicate significant impairments in conversational reciprocity and repetitive speech behaviors among children with ASD. For this administrative supplement, we propose to increase sample size of females with ASD in order to increase statistical power to analyze sex differences among children with ASD in atypical language use. Our rationale for this project is that successful identification of observable and objective differences (and similarities) between females and males in atypical language use would allow clinicians to better recognize, assess, and potentially treat symptoms of ASD in females.&lt;/h1&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>chorrrds: Analisando acordes de músicas brasileiras</title>
      <link>https://alison.rbind.io/post/2018-04-25-chorrrds/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 25 Apr 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://alison.rbind.io/post/2018-04-25-chorrrds/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Olá! Tudo bem? Eu sou a &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/brunaw&#34;&gt;Bruna&lt;/a&gt;, e talvez você já me conheça de algum grupo de R no Telegram ou Facebook, ou mesmo pelo meu outro pacote, o&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;a href=&#34;https://cran.r-project.org/web/packages/vagalumeR/index.html&#34;&gt;vagalumeR&lt;/a&gt;. Eu estou prestes a me formar em Estatística na UFPR, e esse post vai ter muito a ver com o tema do meu trabalho de conclusão de curso, que está sendo feito sob orientação do Professor &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/walmes&#34;&gt;Walmes Zeviani&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Recentemente, eu fiz a primeira versão do pacote do meu TCC, o &lt;code&gt;chorrrds&lt;/code&gt;. Ainda tem muito a ser feito nele, mas os primeiros resultados já são bem legais. O pacote &lt;code&gt;chorrrds&lt;/code&gt; pode ser utilizado para a obtenção acordes de músicas, através da raspagem do site &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.cifraclub.com.br/&#34;&gt;CifraClub&lt;/a&gt;. Junto com o pacote já vêm diversos bancos de dados relativos à música brasileira. Ele já está disponível no CRAN, mas as próximas atualizações devem sair em primeira mão nesse repositório: &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/brunaw/chorrrds&#34; class=&#34;uri&#34;&gt;https://github.com/brunaw/chorrrds&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre class=&#34;r&#34;&gt;&lt;code&gt;# Instalação
devtools::install_github(&amp;quot;brunaw/chorrrds&amp;quot;)
# ou
install.packages(&amp;quot;chorrrds&amp;quot;) # do CRAN
data(package = &amp;quot;chorrrds&amp;quot;)&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A base de dados chamada &lt;code&gt;all&lt;/code&gt;, presente no pacote, contém dados referentes a 106 artistas nacionais, dos genêros: “rock”, “pop”, “sertanejo”, “MPB”, “bossa nova”, “forró”, “reggae” e “samba”. Ela já contém, além das variáveis extraídas com o pacote, as datas de lançamento e a popularidade das músicas, obtidas através da API do &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/tiagomendesdantas/Rspotify&#34;&gt;Spotify&lt;/a&gt;. Os detalhes sobre a seleção dos artistas e combinação dos dados com os do Spotify serão omitidos por enquanto, mas quem quiser falar sobre isso comigo, pode ficar a vontade :)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Então vamos lá. Eu vou começar acertando alguns pontos sobre os dados, já que eles não estão perfeitos, como:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Deixar apenas os anos de lançamento das músicas, e não a data completa;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Encontrar as formas mais simples dos acordes (sem acidentes ou extensões);&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Conectar a base original com a dos genêros dos artistas;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Consertar enarmonias, ou seja, transformar as diferentes versões de um acorde com as mesmas notas em uma coisa só (por exemplo, Gb passa a ser F#, já que na prática eles são iguais).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;pre class=&#34;r&#34;&gt;&lt;code&gt;library(tidyverse)

# Base de gêneros
genre &amp;lt;- chorrrds::genre

da &amp;lt;- chorrrds::all %&amp;gt;% 
  dplyr::mutate(date = stringr::str_extract(date, 
                                            pattern = &amp;quot;[0-9]{4,}&amp;quot;)) %&amp;gt;%
  # Extrai apenas os anos
  dplyr::mutate(date = as.numeric(date), # Deixa as datas como valores numéricos
                acorde = stringr::str_extract(chord, # Extrai as partes fundamentais dos
                                              pattern = &amp;quot;^([A-G]#?b?)&amp;quot;)) %&amp;gt;%  # acordes
  dplyr::filter(date &amp;gt; 1900) %&amp;gt;% # Mantém apenas os anos que fazem sentido
  dplyr::left_join(genre, by = &amp;quot;artist&amp;quot;) %&amp;gt;%  # Traz os gêneros dos artistas
  dplyr::mutate(acorde = case_when( # Contribuição do Julio 
    acorde == &amp;quot;Gb&amp;quot; ~ &amp;quot;F#&amp;quot;,
    acorde == &amp;quot;C#&amp;quot; ~ &amp;quot;Db&amp;quot;,          
    acorde == &amp;quot;G#&amp;quot; ~ &amp;quot;Ab&amp;quot;,
    acorde == &amp;quot;A#&amp;quot; ~ &amp;quot;Bb&amp;quot;,
    acorde == &amp;quot;D#&amp;quot; ~ &amp;quot;Eb&amp;quot;,
    acorde == &amp;quot;E#&amp;quot; ~ &amp;quot;F&amp;quot;,
    acorde == &amp;quot;B#&amp;quot; ~ &amp;quot;C&amp;quot;,
    TRUE ~ acorde)) # Conversão de enarmonias

head(da)&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;table style=&#34;width:100%;&#34;&gt;
&lt;colgroup&gt;
&lt;col width=&#34;5%&#34; /&gt;
&lt;col width=&#34;39%&#34; /&gt;
&lt;col width=&#34;6%&#34; /&gt;
&lt;col width=&#34;6%&#34; /&gt;
&lt;col width=&#34;4%&#34; /&gt;
&lt;col width=&#34;20%&#34; /&gt;
&lt;col width=&#34;7%&#34; /&gt;
&lt;col width=&#34;6%&#34; /&gt;
&lt;/colgroup&gt;
&lt;thead&gt;
&lt;tr class=&#34;header&#34;&gt;
&lt;th align=&#34;right&#34;&gt;date&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th align=&#34;left&#34;&gt;music&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th align=&#34;right&#34;&gt;popul&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th align=&#34;left&#34;&gt;chord&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th align=&#34;left&#34;&gt;key&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th align=&#34;left&#34;&gt;artist&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th align=&#34;left&#34;&gt;acorde&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th align=&#34;left&#34;&gt;genre&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/thead&gt;
&lt;tbody&gt;
&lt;tr class=&#34;odd&#34;&gt;
&lt;td align=&#34;right&#34;&gt;1992&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align=&#34;left&#34;&gt;adriana calcanhotto a fabrica do poema&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align=&#34;right&#34;&gt;51&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align=&#34;left&#34;&gt;Cm&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align=&#34;left&#34;&gt;D#&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align=&#34;left&#34;&gt;adriana calcanhotto&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align=&#34;left&#34;&gt;C&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align=&#34;left&#34;&gt;MPB&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr class=&#34;even&#34;&gt;
&lt;td align=&#34;right&#34;&gt;1992&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align=&#34;left&#34;&gt;adriana calcanhotto a fabrica do poema&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align=&#34;right&#34;&gt;51&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align=&#34;left&#34;&gt;Ab&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align=&#34;left&#34;&gt;D#&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align=&#34;left&#34;&gt;adriana calcanhotto&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align=&#34;left&#34;&gt;Ab&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align=&#34;left&#34;&gt;MPB&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr class=&#34;odd&#34;&gt;
&lt;td align=&#34;right&#34;&gt;1992&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align=&#34;left&#34;&gt;adriana calcanhotto a fabrica do poema&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align=&#34;right&#34;&gt;51&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align=&#34;left&#34;&gt;Db7&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align=&#34;left&#34;&gt;D#&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align=&#34;left&#34;&gt;adriana calcanhotto&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align=&#34;left&#34;&gt;Db&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align=&#34;left&#34;&gt;MPB&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr class=&#34;even&#34;&gt;
&lt;td align=&#34;right&#34;&gt;1992&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align=&#34;left&#34;&gt;adriana calcanhotto a fabrica do poema&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align=&#34;right&#34;&gt;51&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align=&#34;left&#34;&gt;Db7/9&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align=&#34;left&#34;&gt;D#&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align=&#34;left&#34;&gt;adriana calcanhotto&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align=&#34;left&#34;&gt;Db&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align=&#34;left&#34;&gt;MPB&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr class=&#34;odd&#34;&gt;
&lt;td align=&#34;right&#34;&gt;1992&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align=&#34;left&#34;&gt;adriana calcanhotto a fabrica do poema&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align=&#34;right&#34;&gt;51&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align=&#34;left&#34;&gt;Cm&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align=&#34;left&#34;&gt;D#&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align=&#34;left&#34;&gt;adriana calcanhotto&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align=&#34;left&#34;&gt;C&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align=&#34;left&#34;&gt;MPB&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr class=&#34;even&#34;&gt;
&lt;td align=&#34;right&#34;&gt;1992&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align=&#34;left&#34;&gt;adriana calcanhotto a fabrica do poema&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align=&#34;right&#34;&gt;51&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align=&#34;left&#34;&gt;Fm&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align=&#34;left&#34;&gt;D#&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align=&#34;left&#34;&gt;adriana calcanhotto&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align=&#34;left&#34;&gt;F&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align=&#34;left&#34;&gt;MPB&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A base está no formato longo, ou seja, temos uma linha para cada acorde da música, mantendo a sequência na qual eles aparecem no site.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Muito se fala sobre o quanto as músicas no Brasil andam ficando mais “simples”, ou que alguns genêros musicais são mais ricos que outros. Com os dados que temos, será que é possível concluir algo sobre isso olhando simplesmente para a quantidade média de acordes por música ao longo dos anos? Vejamos o gráfico a seguir.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre class=&#34;r&#34;&gt;&lt;code&gt;da_g &amp;lt;- da %&amp;gt;% 
  # 2018 ainda não é um ano completo
  dplyr::mutate(date &amp;lt; 2018) %&amp;gt;%  
  # Agrupamento por data + acorde + musica
  dplyr::group_by(date, genre, music, chord) %&amp;gt;% 
  # Mantém os acordes distintos/ano
  dplyr::summarise(distintos = n_distinct(chord)) %&amp;gt;% 
  dplyr::summarise(cont = n()) %&amp;gt;% 
  # Média de acordes distintos nas músicas/ano
  dplyr::summarise(media = mean(cont), contagem = n()) 


# grafico
p &amp;lt;- da_g %&amp;gt;% 
  ggplot(aes(x = date, y = media)) +
  geom_point(colour = &amp;quot;skyblue3&amp;quot;) +
  facet_wrap(&amp;quot;genre&amp;quot;) +
  scale_fill_hue(c = 55, l = 75) +
  geom_smooth(aes(group = genre), span = 0.65, colour = &amp;quot;white&amp;quot;, 
              fill = &amp;quot;tan&amp;quot;, method = &amp;quot;loess&amp;quot;) +
  labs(x = &amp;quot;Anos&amp;quot;, y = &amp;quot;Média de acordes/música&amp;quot;)

# tema para deixar o gráfico bonitinho
tema &amp;lt;- theme(
  legend.position=&amp;#39;none&amp;#39;, 
  axis.line = element_line(size = 0.5, colour = &amp;quot;tan&amp;quot;),
  panel.grid.major = element_line(
    colour = &amp;quot;black&amp;quot;, size = 0.08, linetype = &amp;quot;dotted&amp;quot;),
  panel.border = element_blank(),
  panel.background = element_blank(),
  strip.background = element_rect(colour = &amp;quot;tan&amp;quot;, fill = &amp;quot;white&amp;quot;, size = 0.6), 
  strip.text = element_text(size = 14),
  axis.title = element_text(size = 14),
  axis.text = element_text(size = 12))
  
p + tema&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://alison.rbind.io/blog/2018-04-25-chorrrds/media-acordes-musicas.png&#34; style=&#34;display: block; margin: auto;&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Claramente, gêneros como o samba, MPB e bossa nova têm, em geral, uma quantidade média de acordes distintos por música muito maior do que os outros. E eles têm mais variação ao longo dos anos também, o que pode ser um reflexo da maior criatividade envolvida nestes genêros. Os menores valores, como é esperado, estão principalmente no sertanejo, que é um genêro conhecidamente mais uniforme na questão harmônica.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Nós podemos avançar um pouco e olhar para os próprios artistas. Quem será que usa as maiores quantidades de acordes distintos em suas composições? Vamos ver o próximo gráfico, que mostra apenas os artistas com mediana maior do que 8 acordes diferentes por música.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre class=&#34;r&#34;&gt;&lt;code&gt;da_g &amp;lt;- da %&amp;gt;%   
  dplyr::mutate(artist = stringr::str_to_title(artist)) %&amp;gt;% 
  # Agrupamento por artista + música
  dplyr::group_by(artist, genre, music) %&amp;gt;% 
  # Mantém os acordes distintos
  dplyr::summarise(distintos = n_distinct(chord)) %&amp;gt;% 
  # Obtém a mediana e quantis de acordes distintos por música/artistas
  dplyr::summarise(med = median(distintos), 
                   contagem = n(),
                   inf = quantile(distintos)[2],
                   sup = quantile(distintos)[4])


# grafico
p &amp;lt;- da_g %&amp;gt;%
  dplyr::filter(med &amp;gt; 8) %&amp;gt;% 
  ggplot(aes(x = reorder(artist, med), y = med)) +
  geom_pointrange(aes(ymin = inf, ymax = sup, colour = genre), size = 0.7) + 
  scale_colour_hue(c = 55, l = 75) +
  coord_flip() +
  labs(colour = &amp;quot;Gênero&amp;quot;, 
       x = &amp;quot;Artistas&amp;quot;, 
       y = &amp;quot;Primeiro quartil, mediana e terceiro quartil&amp;quot;)

# tema
tema &amp;lt;- theme(
  axis.line = element_line(size = 0.5, 
                           colour = &amp;quot;tan&amp;quot;),
  panel.grid.major = element_line(colour = &amp;quot;black&amp;quot;, 
                                  size = 0.08, 
                                  linetype = &amp;quot;dotted&amp;quot;),
  panel.border = element_blank(),
  panel.background = element_blank(),
  axis.text = element_text(size = 12), 
  axis.title.x = element_text(size = 16),
  axis.title.y = element_text(size = 16))

p + tema&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://alison.rbind.io/blog/2018-04-25-chorrrds/stats-artistas.png&#34; style=&#34;display: block; margin: auto;&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;E &lt;em&gt;voilá&lt;/em&gt;. A primeira posição é ocupada por um dos maiores musicistas brasileiros, que é referência internacional em questões de harmonia: Chico Buarque. Logo em seguida, temos o Reinaldo, um dos maiores sambistas que o Brasil já conheceu, e o Pixinguinha, um gênio do choro. E assim a lista segue, com artistas principalmente da bossa nova, samba e MPB. Demora até que apareça o primeiro dos rockeiros nesta lista, que é a Rita Lee. Dos membros do sertanejo, nenhum chega a aparecer no gráfico, mostrando que a “variedade” harmônica deste gênero musical é mesmo bem baixa.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Até agora está legal mas, com música, sempre pode ficar ainda mais. A ideia mais recente que o meu caro orientador &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/walmes&#34;&gt;Walmes Zeviani&lt;/a&gt; teve para o nosso trabalho é de encadear as transições entre os acordes em um diagrama de cordas. Vocês já ouviram falar desse diagrama? Eu mal o conheço e já considero pacas.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;O diagrama de cordas é um método gráfico (e lindo) de explicitar relações entre grupos ou indivíduos. Os grupos ficam arranjados de forma radial/circular, e as cordas que aparecem dentro do círculo demonstram as conexões entre eles e suas forças. Pra quem sabe um pouquinho sobre harmonia, vai ser sensacional ver o quanto isso faz sentido (mas também não vou entrar nesse mérito agora).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;O exemplo que eu vou mostrar aqui é extremamente simples. Antes eu separei, dos acordes “crus” retirados do CifraClub, apenas a parte fundamental deles. Isto é, desconsiderei se um acorde tem notas extras, acidentes e maior/menor. Ou seja, aqui nós só veremos acordes como C, D, B, A#, o miolo da coisa. Podemos perder informação fazendo isso? Sim, e bastante. Mas como eu disse, esse caso é pra ser bem simples mesmo.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Enfim, vamos voltar ao exemplo. A seguir, eu considero como uma “transição” quando um acorde aparece em sequência do outro (exemplo de transição muito comum: dó-sol). O código abaixo constrói o diagrama de cordas através do pacote &lt;code&gt;chordiag&lt;/code&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre class=&#34;r&#34;&gt;&lt;code&gt;devtools::install_github(&amp;quot;mattflor/chorddiag&amp;quot;)&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;pre class=&#34;r&#34;&gt;&lt;code&gt;# Ordenando por círculo das quintas
ordem &amp;lt;- c(&amp;quot;G&amp;quot;, &amp;quot;D&amp;quot;, &amp;quot;A&amp;quot;, &amp;quot;E&amp;quot;, &amp;quot;B&amp;quot;, &amp;quot;F#&amp;quot;, 
           &amp;quot;Db&amp;quot;, &amp;quot;Ab&amp;quot;, &amp;quot;Eb&amp;quot;, &amp;quot;Bb&amp;quot;, &amp;quot;F&amp;quot;, &amp;quot;C&amp;quot;)

da$acorde &amp;lt;- factor(da$acorde, levels = ordem)

comp &amp;lt;- data.frame(
  acorde = da$acorde, 
  seq = dplyr::lead(da$acorde)) %&amp;gt;% # Pega o acorde &amp;quot;seguinte&amp;quot;
  dplyr::group_by(acorde, seq) %&amp;gt;%  # Agrupa por cada transição
  dplyr::summarise(contagem = n()) # Conta quantas são as transições

mat_comp &amp;lt;- reshape2::dcast(comp,   # Arranja em do tipo matriz quadrada
                            acorde ~ seq, value.var = &amp;quot;contagem&amp;quot;) 
mm &amp;lt;- as.matrix(mat_comp[ ,-1]) # Converte o df em matriz (exigência do pacote)
mm[is.na(mm)] &amp;lt;- 0 # Substitui na por 0 (exigência do pacote)
dimnames(mm) &amp;lt;- list(acorde = unique(mat_comp$acorde),
                     seq = unique(mat_comp$acorde))

# Constrói o diagrama interativo
chorddiag::chorddiag(mm, showTicks = FALSE,
                     palette = &amp;quot;Set2&amp;quot;, palette2 = &amp;quot;#Set3&amp;quot;)&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;center&gt;
&lt;iframe src=&#34;https://r-music.github.io/rday-2018/docs/chorrrds&#34; width=&#34;100%&#34; height=&#34;650&#34; frameborder=&#34;0&#34; scrolling=&#34;no&#34; marginheight=&#34;0&#34; marginwidth=&#34;0&#34;&gt;
&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;/center&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Vejam que interessante. Como eu disse antes, uma das relações mais fortes do diagrama é o C-G (ou dó-sol), que é justificada teoricamente, já que o G é a quinta do C. O mesmo acontece com D-A, A-E, F-C e assim por diante. Quem quiser saber mais sobre esse comportamento, pode dar uma olhada &lt;a href=&#34;https://ledgernote.com/columns/music-theory/circle-of-fifths-explained/&#34;&gt;aqui&lt;/a&gt;. Transições meio malucas, como B-Bb, também acontecem. “Maluca” porque um acorde bemol, indicado pelo “b”, é aquele cuja raíz esta meio tom abaixo do indicado pela letra anterior, que neste caso é o B (si), então esse acontecimento não faz muito sentido.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;consideracoes-finais&#34; class=&#34;section level1&#34;&gt;
&lt;h1&gt;Considerações Finais&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;O que vimos aqui é um pedaço da análise inicial do meu TCC, que ainda não está nem um pouco pronto. São exemplos simples das informações podemos extrair com o pacote &lt;code&gt;chorrrds&lt;/code&gt;, e o universo de possibilidades é infinito. Isso que nós nem começamos a falar sobre as conexões que podem ser feitas com a API do Spotify, o pacote &lt;code&gt;music21&lt;/code&gt;, que é do próprio Julio Trecenti, com as letras das músicas,…&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Além disso, om certeza, meu objetivo com os gráficos apresentados não é fazer nenhum tipo de juízo de valor sobre os genêros por conta de “complexidade harmônica”. Diga-se de passagem, eu mesma sou bem fã de todos esses genêros, desde a MPB até o sertanejo :D&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;agradecimentos&#34; class=&#34;section level1&#34;&gt;
&lt;h1&gt;Agradecimentos&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ao meu orientador, &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/walmes&#34;&gt;Walmes Zeviani&lt;/a&gt;, que fez eu me apaixonar pelo R, e ao &lt;a href=&#34;http://curso-r.com/author/julio/&#34;&gt;Julio Trecenti&lt;/a&gt;, que é tão entusiasta do meu TCC quanto eu, e já fez diversas contribuições valiosas.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Aplicações simples do pacote vagalumeR</title>
      <link>https://alison.rbind.io/post/2017-06-25-vagalumer/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 25 Jun 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://alison.rbind.io/post/2017-06-25-vagalumer/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;O site &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.vagalume.com.br&#34; class=&#34;uri&#34;&gt;https://www.vagalume.com.br&lt;/a&gt; é um lugar aonde podemos obter informações sobre músicas, com foco nas letras e traduções delas. Este site possui uma API, que pode ser acessada no &lt;code&gt;R&lt;/code&gt; através do pacote &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/brunaw/vagalumeR&#34;&gt;vagalumeR&lt;/a&gt;. Aqui, demonstra-se algumas funcionalidades do pacote, sendo uma das mais interessantes delas a análise das letras das músicas.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre class=&#34;r&#34;&gt;&lt;code&gt;# Carregamento de pacotes
library(vagalumeR)
library(tidyverse)
library(tm)
library(lattice)
library(lexiconPT)
library(latticeExtra)
library(wordcloud)
library(networkD3)

packageVersion(&amp;quot;vagalumeR&amp;quot;)&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Para acessar a API, é preciso que o usuário possua um &lt;code&gt;token&lt;/code&gt;, que pode ser obtido no endereço: &lt;a href=&#34;https://auth.vagalume.com.br/settings/api/&#34; class=&#34;uri&#34;&gt;https://auth.vagalume.com.br/settings/api/&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre class=&#34;r&#34;&gt;&lt;code&gt;key &amp;lt;- &amp;quot;insira seu token&amp;quot;&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;pre class=&#34;r&#34;&gt;&lt;code&gt;# Seleção de algum artista
artist &amp;lt;- &amp;quot;chico-buarque&amp;quot;

# Informações sobre o artista
(info &amp;lt;- artistInfo(artist))

# Discografia do artista
disc &amp;lt;- discography(artist)
head(disc, 10)

# Contagem de discos por ano
xtabs(~date, disc)

# Artistas relacionados
(rel &amp;lt;- relatedInfo(artist))[,4]

# Busca de letras de músicas do artista
song &amp;lt;- songNames(artist)
let &amp;lt;- plyr::ldply(map(song$song.id[1:10], lyrics, type = &amp;quot;id&amp;quot;, key = key),
             data.frame)

str(let)

#------------------------------------------------------------------# Frequência de Palavras
#------------------------------------------------------------------
# Cria o Corpus e limpa 
cps &amp;lt;- VCorpus(VectorSource(let$text),
                 readerControl = list(language = &amp;quot;pt&amp;quot;))
cps &amp;lt;- tm_map(cps, FUN = content_transformer(tolower))
cps &amp;lt;- tm_map(cps, FUN = removePunctuation)
cps &amp;lt;- tm_map(cps, FUN = removeNumbers)
cps &amp;lt;- tm_map(cps, FUN = stripWhitespace)
cps &amp;lt;- tm_map(cps,
                FUN = removeWords,
                words = stopwords(&amp;quot;portuguese&amp;quot;))
cps &amp;lt;- tm_map(cps,
                FUN = removeWords,
                words = &amp;quot;\t&amp;quot;)

# Cria a matriz de documentos e termos
dtm &amp;lt;- DocumentTermMatrix(cps)

# Características da dtm
inspect(dtm)

# Termos com uma certa frequência miníma
tms &amp;lt;- findFreqTerms(dtm, lowfreq = 3)
str(tms)

# Termos que são associados
assoc &amp;lt;- findAssocs(dtm, terms = tms, corlimit = 0.9)
b &amp;lt;- data.frame(pal = &amp;quot;amor&amp;quot;, assoc = names(assoc$amor))

# Visualização de associação entre palavras
simpleNetwork(b,
              opacity = 0.8, 
              linkColour= &amp;quot;violet&amp;quot;, 
              nodeColour=&amp;quot;tomato&amp;quot;, 
              zoom=TRUE, fontSize = 16,
              linkDistance = 70)

# Contagem das palavras
frq &amp;lt;- slam::colapply_simple_triplet_matrix(dtm, FUN = sum)
frq &amp;lt;- sort(frq, decreasing = TRUE)

# Gráfico da contagem das 30 palavras mais frequentes
barchart(head(frq, n = 30), xlim = c(0, NA),
         col =  &amp;quot;lightsalmon&amp;quot;, 
         xlab = &amp;quot;Frequência&amp;quot;,
         ylab = &amp;quot;Palavras&amp;quot;,
         main = &amp;quot;Paravras em músicas do Chico Buarque&amp;quot;,
         strip = strip.custom(bg = &amp;quot;white&amp;quot;))

# O mesmo resultado visto em nuvem
wordcloud(cps,
          family = &amp;quot;serif&amp;quot;, 
          min.freq = 3,
          max.words = 30,
          colors = brewer.pal(7, &amp;quot;Paired&amp;quot;))

#------------------------------------------------------------------
# Atribuição de Polaridades
#------------------------------------------------------------------

# Dicionário de sentimentos do pacote lexiconPT
dic &amp;lt;- lexiconPT::oplexicon_v3.0
str(dic)

# Intersecção entre termos das músicas e os que estão
# no dicionário
inter &amp;lt;- intersect(x = Terms(dtm),
                   y = dic$term)
length(inter)

# Traz as polaridades para as palavras das músicas
lex &amp;lt;- merge(x = data.frame(term = inter,
                            stringsAsFactors = FALSE),
             y = dic,
             sort = FALSE)
head(lex, 10)

# Tranzforma a dtm em matriz ordinária
m &amp;lt;- as.matrix(dtm)
m &amp;lt;- m[, lex$term]

# Somas por linhas da matriz
rtot &amp;lt;- rowSums(m)

# &amp;quot;Cargas&amp;quot; de cada música
(carga &amp;lt;- (m %*% lex$polarity)/rtot)

# Soma de polaridades por música
m %*% cbind(lex$polarity)

# Função que traz as proporções de cada polaridade por música
pp &amp;lt;- function(song){
  
  cps &amp;lt;- VCorpus(VectorSource(song),
                 readerControl = list(language = &amp;quot;pt&amp;quot;))
  cps &amp;lt;- tm_map(cps, FUN = content_transformer(tolower))
  cps &amp;lt;- tm_map(cps, FUN = removePunctuation)
  cps &amp;lt;- tm_map(cps, FUN = removeNumbers)
  cps &amp;lt;- tm_map(cps, FUN = stripWhitespace)
  cps &amp;lt;- tm_map(cps,
                FUN = removeWords,
                words = stopwords(&amp;quot;portuguese&amp;quot;))
  cps &amp;lt;- tm_map(cps,
                FUN = removeWords,
                words = &amp;quot;\t&amp;quot;)
  
  dtm &amp;lt;- DocumentTermMatrix(cps)
  
  inter &amp;lt;- intersect(x = Terms(dtm),
                     y = dic$term)
  
  lex &amp;lt;- merge(x = data.frame(term = inter,
                              stringsAsFactors = FALSE),
               y = dic,
               sort = FALSE)
  
  pp &amp;lt;- c(prop.table(xtabs(~polarity, lex)))
  
  return(pp)  
}
# Porcentagens de cada polaridade por música
(pcs &amp;lt;- plyr::ldply(map(let$text, pp), matrix, ncol = 3))
names(pcs) &amp;lt;- c(&amp;quot;neg&amp;quot;, &amp;quot;neutro&amp;quot;, &amp;quot;pos&amp;quot;)

# Curva da distribuição acumulada dos sentimentos
ecdfplot(~pos+neg+neutro, pcs, 
         col = c(&amp;quot;tomato&amp;quot;, &amp;quot;turquoise&amp;quot;, &amp;quot;orange&amp;quot;),
         key = list(columns = 1,
                    corner = c(0.05, 0.9),
                    lines = list(col = c(&amp;quot;tomato&amp;quot;, &amp;quot;turquoise&amp;quot;,
                                         &amp;quot;orange&amp;quot;)),
                                 text = list(c(&amp;quot;neg&amp;quot;, &amp;quot;neutro&amp;quot;,
                                               &amp;quot;pos&amp;quot;))))&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Non Linear Modelling</title>
      <link>https://alison.rbind.io/project/nlmset/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://alison.rbind.io/project/nlmset/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;h1 id=&#34;targeting-core-symptoms-of-autism-spectrum-disorders-asd-is-a-key-treatment-goal-for-parents-of-children-with-asd-while-many-efficacious-treatments-for-asd-have-been-developed-a-major-obstacle-in-evaluating-these-treatments-among-children-with-asd-has-been-the-lack-of-adequate-outcome-measures-anagnostou-et-al-2014-bolte-diehl-2013-kanne-et-al-2014-most-treatment-studies-have-relied-on-informant-based-measures-i-e-parent-or-clinician-report-that-either-place-a-high-burden-on-families-or-require-significant-training-and-time-to-administer-moreover-measures-are-often-re-purposed-from-existing-measures-intended-for-screening-or-diagnosis-and-do-not-provide-continuous-measures-of-symptoms-that-are-responsive-to-change-thus-there-is-a-clear-need-to-develop-asd-outcome-measures-that-are-reliable-valid-and-sensitive-to-change-in-the-absence-of-such-outcome-measures-our-understanding-of-the-efficacy-of-treatments-for-asd-will-continue-to-be-limited&#34;&gt;Targeting core symptoms of Autism Spectrum Disorders (ASD) is a key treatment goal for parents of children with ASD. While many efficacious treatments for ASD have been developed, a major obstacle in evaluating these treatments among children with ASD has been the lack of adequate outcome measures (Anagnostou et al., 2014; Bolte &amp;amp; Diehl, 2013; Kanne et al., 2014). Most treatment studies have relied on informant-based measures (i.e., parent or clinician report) that either place a high burden on families, or require significant training and time to administer. Moreover, measures are often re-purposed from existing measures intended for screening or diagnosis, and do not provide continuous measures of symptoms that are responsive to change. Thus, there is a clear need to develop ASD outcome measures that are reliable, valid, and sensitive to change. In the absence of such outcome measures, our understanding of the efficacy of treatments for ASD will continue to be limited.&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&#34;at-the-same-time-automated-methods-for-quantifying-behavior-have-become-more-advanced-less-intrusive-and-more-cost-effective-and-could-provide-reliable-and-sensitive-measures-of-behavioral-change-however-these-methods-have-yet-to-be-translated-into-a-viable-outcome-measure-for-use-in-treatment-studies-for-example-recent-research-has-shown-that-autism-symptoms-can-be-objectively-measured-with-automated-methods-such-as-eye-tracking-rice-moriuchi-jones-klin-2012-natural-language-processing-gorman-et-al-2016-rouhizadeh-et-al-2014-van-santen-sproat-hill-2013-and-quantitative-facial-emotion-analysis-metallinou-grossman-narayanan-2013-and-that-such-measures-are-interpretable-and-meaningful-for-the-everyday-lives-of-children-and-their-families&#34;&gt;At the same time, automated methods for quantifying behavior have become more advanced, less intrusive, and more cost-effective, and could provide reliable and sensitive measures of behavioral change. However, these methods have yet to be translated into a viable outcome measure for use in treatment studies. For example, recent research has shown that autism symptoms can be objectively measured with automated methods such as eye-tracking (Rice, Moriuchi, Jones, &amp;amp; Klin, 2012), natural language processing (Gorman et al., 2016; Rouhizadeh et al., 2014; van Santen, Sproat, &amp;amp; Hill, 2013), and quantitative facial emotion analysis (Metallinou, Grossman, &amp;amp; Narayanan, 2013), and that such measures are interpretable and meaningful for the everyday lives of children and their families.&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&#34;the-goal-of-this-project-is-to-develop-and-validate-a-novel-objective-measurement-tool-the-multi-modal-autism-phenotype-snapshot-maps-for-use-in-clinical-trials-targeting-core-symptoms-of-autism-maps-uses-automated-methods-to-measure-autism-relevant-behaviors-across-multiple-modalities-gaze-tracking-natural-language-processing-facial-expression-analysis-while-children-watch-and-respond-to-audiovisual-stimuli-presented-on-a-laptop-this-project-was-funded-by-a-catalyst-award-from-the-oregon-clinical-translational-research-institute&#34;&gt;The goal of this project is to develop and validate a novel objective measurement tool, the Multi-modal Autism Phenotype Snapshot (MAPS), for use in clinical trials targeting core symptoms of autism. MAPS uses automated methods to measure autism-relevant behaviors across multiple modalities (gaze-tracking, natural language processing, facial expression analysis) while children watch and respond to audiovisual stimuli presented on a laptop. This project was funded by a Catalyst Award from the Oregon Clinical &amp;amp; Translational Research Institute.&lt;/h1&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
